Rae Korson papers, 1937-1982
American Folklife Center, Library of Congress
Rae Korson papers 1937-1982
AFC 1986/003
Korson, Rae, collector, creator
approximately 1787 items
5 containers
2.5 linear feet
approximately 1774 sheets
13 photographic prints: black-and-white; various sizes
American Folklife Center, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Collection of correspondence, Library of Congress-related personnel documentation, and ephemera related to Rae Korson's tenure at the Archive of Folk Song. Correspondents include: Jan Brunvand, Sidney Robertson Cowell, Archie Green, Alta Fife, Austin Fife, Helen Hartness Flanders, Frank Gillis, Wayland Hand, Herbert Halpert, Joe Hickerson, Charles Hofmann, Charles Iler, Sandy Ives, Bruce Jackson, Maud Karpeles, George List, Judith McCulloh, Peter Nabokov, Bruno Nettl, Willard Rhodes, Ralph Rinzler, Ruth Rubin, Charles Seeger, Francis Lee Utley, Naomi Ware, Frank Warner, Dick Waterman, D.K. Wilgus, Henrietta Yurchenco, and others.
Provenance
Rae Korson; Donation, 1986.
Accruals
No accruals are expected.
Related Material
WPA folklore publications collected by Rae Korson (AFC 1939/004), American Folklife Center, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.
Korson Day reception collection (AFC 1981/039), American Folklife Center, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.
Access and Restrictions
The Rae Korson Papers is open to research. To request materials, please contact the Folklife Reading Room at https://hdl.loc.gov/loc.afc/folklife.contact
Certain restrictions to use or copying of materials may apply.
Biographical Note
Rae Korson began her career at the Archive of Folk Song at the Library of Congress as a reference assistant in 1942. She eventually became Head of the Archive in 1956 and served in that position until 1969.
Scope and Content
Collection of correspondence, Library of Congress-related personnel documentation, and ephemera related to Rae Korson's tenure at the Archive of Folk Song. Correspondents include: Jan Brunvand, Sidney Robertson Cowell, Archie Green, Alta Fife, Austin Fife, Helen Hartness Flanders, Frank Gillis, Wayland Hand, Herbert Halpert, Joe Hickerson, Charles Hofmann, Charles Iler, Sandy Ives, Bruce Jackson, Maud Karpeles, George List, Judith McCulloh, Peter Nabokov, Bruno Nettl, Willard Rhodes, Ralph Rinzler, Ruth Rubin, Charles Seeger, Francis Lee Utley, Naomi Ware, Frank Warner, Dick Waterman, D.K. Wilgus, Henrietta Yurchenco, and others.
Arrangement
The Rae Korson Papers is organized in six series:
Series 1: Correspondence
Series 2: Library of Congress and the Archive of Folk Song
Series 3: Folk studies and activities
Series 4: News coverage
Series 5: Offprints and serials
Series 6: Graphic materials
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Brunvand, Jan Harold--Correspondence.; Cowell, Sidney Robertson, 1903-1995--Correspondence.; Fife, Alta (Alta Stevens), 1912-1996--Correspondence.; Fife, Austin E.--Correspondence.; Flanders, Helen Hartness, 1890-1972--Correspondence.; Gillis, Frank--Correspondence.; Green, Archie--Correspondence.; Halpert, Herbert, 1911-2000--Correspondence.; Hand, Wayland D. (Wayland Debs), 1907-1986--Correspondence.; Hickerson, Joseph C. (Joseph Charles), 1935- --Correspondence.; Hofmann, Charles, 1914-1996--Correspondence.; Iler, Charles A., 1891-1963--Correspondence.; Ives, Edward D.--Correspondence.; Jackson, Bruce, 1936- --Correspondence.; Karpeles, Maud, 1885-1976--Correspondence.; Korson, Rae; Korson, Rae--Correspondence.; List, George, 1911-2008--Correspondence.; McCulloh, Judith, 1935-2014--Correspondence.; Nabokov, Peter--Correspondence.; Nettl, Bruno, 1930-2020--Correspondence.; Rhodes, Willard, 1901-1992--Correspondence.; Rinzler, Ralph--Correspondence.; Rubin, Ruth--Correspondence.; Seeger, Charles, 1886-1979--Correspondence.; Utley, Francis Lee, 1907-1974--Correspondence.; Ware, Naomi--Correspondence.; Warner, Frank, 1903-1978--Correspondence.; Waterman, Dick--Correspondence.; Wilgus, D. K.--Correspondence.; Yurchenco, Henrietta--Correspondence.
Organizations
American Folklife Center.; Archive of Folk Song (U.S.); Archive of Folk Song (U.S.); Library of Congress--Officials and employees.; Library of Congress. Music Division.
Subjects
Folklore archives--United States.
Form/Genre
Correspondence.; Manuscripts.; Photographs.
Container List
- Series 1: Correspondence
  Items include typed and handwritten correspondence (letters, notes, and postcards). While most are originals there are duplicates and drafts. Some items are accompanied by the original postal envelopes. Some ephemera (newspaper clippings, brochures, etc.) accompany items.
  - Correspondence, 1947-1959 (Box-folder 1/1)
    Correspondents and recipients include Dorothy Berliner Cummins, Helen Bullard Kreckniak, Edward M. Coffman, Ray M. Lawless, and Duncan Emrich.
  - Correspondence, 1960 (Box-folder 1/2)
    Correspondents and recipients include Arthur McAnally, Howard Mitchell, Gordon Hitchcock, Alfred Frankenstein, Lou Blachly, Andrew Forest Muir, Theodore Alevizos, Henry Allen Moe, Dena Epstein, Perkins Bass, William Widnall, and Alta and Austin Fife.
  - Correspondence, 1961 (Box-folder 1/3)
    Correspondents and recipients include Gottfried Wolters, Jean Woodward Steele, Sherman Lee Pompey, Philip Joseph Philbin, Rolf Myklebust, Ray M. Lawless, Wilfried Brennecke, Lila Cheville, Wayland Hand, Rolf Italiaander, Robert Nye, and Adeline McCall.
  - Correspondence, 1962 (Box-folder 1/4)
    Correspondents and recipients include Joseph Hall, Ben Gray Lumpkin, Alta Fife, Maud Karpeles, Henry Allen Moe, Howard Mitchell, Ruth Rubin, Joe Hickerson, Joan Shigekawa, Richard Dorson, John Burrison, Herbert Halpert, Peter Nabokov, Vince Martin, Francis Lee Utley, and Helen Hartness Flanders.
  - Correspondence, January-June 1963 (Box-folder 1/5)
    Correspondents and recipients include Maud Karpeles, Sarah Gertrude Knott, Ed Cray, Willard Rhodes, William N. Fenton, Anne Grimes, John Burrison, Mamie Meredith, Jan Brunvand, Annabel Morris Buchanan, and Halim El-Dabh.
  - Correspondence, July-December 1963 (Box-folder 1/6)
    Correspondents and recipients include Arthur Luce Klein, Kenneth Goldstein, John Greenway, Sterling A. Brown, Jac Holzman, Bruno Nettl, John Greenway, Harold Spivacke, Bruce Jackson, Ruth Rubin, Willard Rhodes, and Ellen Stekert.
  - Correspondence, 1964 (Box-folder 1/7)
    Correspondents and recipients include Negley K. Teeters, Jac Holzman, Archie Green, James G. Fulton, Ann Moray, Harry Oster, Evelyn K. Wells, Donald Shaw Ramsey, Charles Seeger, Norman Cazden, Ralph Rinzler, James J. Fuld, Bruce Jackson, Henrietta Yurchenco, and Wayland Hand.
  - Correspondence, 1965 (Box-folder 2/1)
    Correspondents and recipients include Hubert Humphrey, Frank Warner, Helen Bullard [Helen Bullard Kreckniak], Frank Gillis, Sandy Ives, Arthur F. Schrader, Judith McCulloh, Jan Brunvand, Laura Boulton, Maud Karpeles, Helga Sandburg, Annabel Morris Buchanan, Pete Seeger, Dick Waterman, Helen Hartness Flanders, Alice Hutchins Drake, Harold Spivacke, and Willard Rhodes.
  - Correspondence, 1966 (Box-folder 2/2)
    Correspondents and recipients include Archie Green, Sandy Ives, Helen Bullard [Helen Bullard Kreckniak], Beatrice Kane McLain, Herbert Halpert, Austin Fife, Harold Spivacke, Charles Seeger, D.K. Wilgus, Frank Gillis, Sidney Robertson Cowell, and Will Geer.
  - Correspondence, 1967 (Box-folder 2/3)
    Correspondents and recipients include John Meredith Langstaff, Charles H. Faurot, D.K. Wilgus, Barbara Krader, Harry Oster, Bernard Klatzko, Edith Fowke, Alan Jabbour, Frank Gillis, Ruth Rubin, Don Yoder, Bruce Jackson, Austin Fife, Alta Fife, Henry Glassie, and Benjamin Botkin.
  - Correspondence, January-May 1968 (Box-folder 2/4)
    Correspondents and recipients include Don Yoder, Bernard Klatzko, Benjamin Botkin, Austin Fife, Ruth Rubin, Archie Green, Oscar Brand, Dick Reuss [Richard A. Reuss], Alfred Frankenstein, Marie Kiersted Pidgeon, Wayland Hand, Helen Hartness Flanders, Archie Green, Richard Dorson, Carl Withers, Michael Cooney, and Richard Nixon.
  - Correspondence, June-December 1968 (Box-folder 2/5)
    Correspondents and recipients include Willard Rhodes, Alfred Frankenstein, Marie Kiersted Pidgeon, Wayland Hand, Helen Hartness Flanders, Archie Green, Richard Dorson, Oscar Brand, and Michael Cooney.
  - Correspondence, 1969 (Box-folder 2/6)
    Correspondents and recipients include Willard Rhodes, Helen Creighton, William N. Fenton, Helga Sandburg, Hilda Kring, Joe Glazer, Francis Utley, Theodore Grame, Dieter Christensen, and L. Quincy Mumford. A black-and-white photo of a house in this folder, sent by Hilda Kring.
  - Correspondence, 1982 (Box-folder 2/7)
    Correspondents and recipients include Willard Rhodes and Claire Marwick.
  - Correspondence, undated (Box-folder 2/8)
    Correspondents and recipients include Charles Seeger and Carolyn Hester.
- Series 2: Library of Congress and the Archive of Folk Song
  - LC Information Bulletin, circa 1950s-1960s (Box-folder 3/1-2)
    Includes complete and partial issues. Most are originals, with some photocopies, plus a typed draft notice for the April 1, 1966 issue.
  - LC press releases, 1962-1967, undated (Box-folder 3/3)
  - LC official communications, 1961-1969, undated (Box-folder 3/4)
    Includes memos, orders, regulations, announcements, and circulars.
  - Recommending officers, 1960-1969, undated (Box-folder 3/5)
    Lists of LC staff members from various divisions and their area(s) of expertise.
  - Music Division, Library of Congress: inventories, 1960-1969, undated (Box-folder 3/6)
    Includes inventories related to the Archive of Folk Song.
  - Archive of Folk Song: descriptions and holdings, 1940-1966, undated (Box-folder 3/7)
    Also includes a page from the annual report, for the year ending 1959.
  - Reading room visitors: Archive of Folk Song and Recording Laboratory, 1960-1967, undated (Box-folder 3/8)
  - Serial orders: administrative documents and notes, 1954-1966, undated (Box-folder 3/9-10)
  - Personnel file: Rae Korson, 1947-1969, undated (Box-folder 4/1)
    Korson's copy of documents related to her employment, rather than the official personnel file. Includes job descriptions, performance rating documents and notices related to promotions and advancements, handwritten notes, selected pages from the LC Information Bulletin, and other documents. The folder also includes the vita sheet for Donald H. Winkelman, and a copy of a memo to Mr. Berry, recommending the appointment of Alan Jabbour to the position of Head of the Archive of Folk Song.
  - Travel, 1954-1968, undated (Box-folder 4/2)
    Travel itineraries, copies of official leave requests, and related documents.
- Series 3: Folk studies and activities
  Events, organizations, and promotional materials related to folk studies and activities.
  - Professional meetings, organizations, and related documents, 1961-1969, undated (Box-folder 4/3)
    Documents related to meetings of the American Folklore Society (AFS) and the Society for Ethnomusicology (SEM), as well as travel-related documents.
  - Institutional news, public events, and announcements, 1957-1982, undated (Box-folder 4/4)
    Includes a program inscribed and signed by Odetta.
  - Writings, reviews, and related documents, 1960-1967, undated (Box-folder 4/5)
    Includes typed and handwritten documents, most in draft form.
  - Notes, circa 1960s (Box-folder 4/6)
    Most are handwritten notes on various topics, probably transitory in nature.
  - Malapropisms, circa 1960s (Box-folder 4/7)
    Typed compilations from various sources.
  - New books and recordings, 1961-1968, undated (Box-folder 4/8)
    Includes announcements for new publications and sound recordings, and related promotional literature. A Passover haggadah (in Hebrew and English) is included; kept with related materials received together, to preserve the integrity of the materials as a group.
- Series 4: News coverage
  - Clippings, circa 1950s-1960s (Box-folder 5/1-4)
    Includes magazine and newspaper clippings, and some complete sections.
- Series 5: Offprints and serials
  - Offprints and serials, 1952-1968, undated (Box-folder 5/5-7)
    Offprints from various publications, selected complete issues of serials, and other publications. Includes music booklets, bulletins from folk music and folklore-related organizations, writings by folklore scholars including Archie Green and Benjamin A. Botkin, and Library of Congress publications. Some items are inscribed by authors to Rae Korson.
- Series 6: Graphic materials
  - Black-and-white photos (Box-folder 5/8)
  - The family of Thomas Wolfe, before his birth, July 4, 1899, AFC 1986/003: PH01; 1 photo: black-and-white gelatin emulsion print, 5 3/4 in. x 3 1/2 in. or smaller
    Copy of the original image. The family of Thomas Wolfe; his siblings and parents, in front of their Asheville home at 92 Woodfin Street.
  - Thomas Wolfe, circa 1937, AFC 1986/003: PH02; 1 photo: black-and-white gelatin emulsion print, 5 3/4 in. x 3 1/2 in. or smaller
    Assumed to be a copy of the original image.
  - May Kennedy McCord, circa 1940s-1950s, AFC 1986/003: PH03; 1 photographic image: blue and white on coated paper stock, 5 1/2 in. x 3 1/2 in. or smaller
    Copy of a promotional image.
  - Vance Randolph, July 1958, AFC 1986/003: PH04; 1 photo: black-and-white gelatin emulsion print, 5 in. x 4 in. or smaller; Jan Brunvand
  - Archer Taylor, July 1958, AFC 1986/003: PH05; 1 photo: black-and-white gelatin emulsion print, 5 in. x 4 in. or smaller; Jan Brunvand
  - Jim Smart and Rae Korson, July 1963, AFC 1986/003: PH06; 1 photo: black-and-white gelatin emulsion print, 2 1/2 in. x 2 1/2 in. or smaller; H. Spivacke
  - Rae Korson, an unidentified man, and an unidentified woman, 1968, AFC 1986/003: PH07; 1 photo: black-and-white print, 5 1/2 in. x 3 1/2 in. or smaller
    Memento photo in a presentation/keepsake holder, printed with the words "Vacances 1968 / Courchevel 1850." Courchevel 1850 was and is a resort in Courchevel, France.
  - Grotto at Old Economy Village, Cambridge, Pennsylvania, undated, AFC 1986/003: PH08; 1 photo: black-and-white gelatin emulsion print, 4 1/2 in. x 3 1/2 in. or smaller
    Handwritten on the verso: "The Grotto at old Economy, Cambridge, Pa. Enclosed is Myra's letter. Thought you could stay at the same place. Looking forward to seeing you. Fondly, Hilda." The photo is stored in Box-folder 2/6 with Hilda Kring's letter.
  - Sam Holmes, June 1964, AFC 1986/003: PH09; 1 photo: black-and-white gelatin emulsion print, 3 1/2 in. x 5 in.; Bruce Jackson
    The photo is stored in Box-folder 1/7, in the folder with the Bruce Jackson letter.
  - Folklore store front, in Chamonix, France, July 1961, AFC 1986/003: PH10; 1 photo: black-and-white gelatin emulsion print, 8 in. x 10 in.
    Image of a store front with signage indicating its name or more likely what it sells is "Folklore." Photographed from the street, with people and goods in the photo. The photographer's name handwritten on the verso may be "Mr. Apivailu."
  - Rae Korson, probably at the Library of Congress, February 1963, AFC 1986/003: PH11; 1 photo: black-and-white gelatin emulsion print, 8 in. x 10 in.
    Rae Korson, seated in a chair next to crates of materials, posed as if filing a 10-inch commercial sound disc in its sleeve. Photo by Joseph Silverman (Star staff).
  - Retirement event for Pauline Bollenbacher, probably at the Library of Congress; from left: Robert S. Bray, Pauline Bollenbacher, Dr. L. Quincy Mumford, December 16, 1966, AFC 1986/003: PH12; 1 photo: black-and-white gelatin emulsion print, 8 in. x 10 in.
    Robert S. Bray was at that time the Chief of the Division for the Blind. Pauline Bollenbacher was the selection officer for the Library's Division for the Blind. Dr. Mumford was the Librarian of Congress (1954-1974). Photograph taken by Library of Congress staff.
  - Burl Ives in the Library of Congress recording studio, 1950, AFC 1986/003: PH13; 1 photo: black-and-white gelatin emulsion print, 8 in. x 10 in.
    Ives is posed before a mic and holding a guitar, as if singing to the young boy sitting on a desk. Photograph taken by Library of Congress staff. See the Prints and Photographs Division digital version of the same image.